欢迎来到 eLearning 课程
HL7数据转换入门。
当我们在不同系统减交换数据时候，
常需要将一条记录或消息结构映射
到另外一条稍微不同的记录或消息上。
如同当我们从一个应用发送 Hl7 消息
到另一个应用，常需要
转换数据，那样接受方可以
接受到正确格式的数据。
比如，也许你有一个治疗医嘱消息进来，
其会触发一个 EDT 消息，
而这个消息需要根据医嘱消息的
的一些内容发送。
或者你有个消息进来，
根据消息中病人特定的州或国家
需要做出一些决定。
有很多不同的事情，你可能需要消息
以某种格式
适合接受应用的需求。
我们会从一些基础的例子讲起。
让我们从一个简单的数据转换开始。
To create a new
transformation, let's go
要创建新数据转换，让我们到
管理门户
我们可以选中 Build, Data Transformation 菜单
然后点击 "New".
从这个向导中，我们可以获得设置的选项。
首先，我们需要给它一个合适的名字。
有多个数据转换是非常常见的，
所以起一个有用的名字可允许你能快速
断定你所需要使用的数据转换。
我们来命名它"ADTDTL",
因为我们将建立一个转换
做病人的入院信息。
We then need to
specify a source class.
然后我们需要指定一个源类。
For HL7 messages, we are going
to be using EnsLib.HL7Message.
对于 HL7 消息，我们会用 EnsLib.HL7Message.
However, if we simply
click the HL7 radio,
然而，如果我们只是简单的选中 HL7 的单选按钮，
this will be automatically
added for us.
就会自动替我们添加这个类。
We then need to choose
our Source Doc Type.
然后我们只需要选择源的文档类型。
Our doc type that we're going
to choose is 2.3.1 ADT_A01.
我们的文档类型会选为 2.3.1 ADT_A01.
This wizard will automatically
set up our targets
向导会自动地为我们将目标设置
be the same as my source,
but we can always change
为同我们的源一样,但是可以随时修改
that to be different values.
成不同的值。
For this case, our
target and our source
在这个例子中，我们的目标和源
are going to be the same type.
会用同一类型的数据。
Then we can click OK.
然后我们点击 OK。
Notice here we get a
blank Data Transformation.
注意到，这里，我们取得的是一个空的数据转换。
We have our source, which
is of type 2.3.1 ADT_A01,
我们的源数据的类型是 2.3.1 ADT_A01,
and our target, which
is also 2.3.1 ADT_A01.
并且我们的目标数据也是 2.3.1 ADT_A01.
The first thing that we
want to do to set this up
首先我们要做的在
is to go to the Transform
tab on the right.
右边的 Transform 标签页中进行设置。
The first thing to do is to
set up the Create property
第一我们要做的是在 Transform 标签页中
from the Transform tab.
设置 "Create" 属性。
We're going to choose New.
我们会选者 "New".
This means that
the target is going
这意味着目标值
to start completely empty.
起始为空。
If we did copy, the
entire source message
如果我们选择的是 "Copy",整个源消息
would be the starting
place for the target.
会被复制在目标消息中。
Typically, you only
want to do this
通常，你只有在文档类型
if the doc types are the same.
相同的时候才这么做。
Let's start by mapping all
the corresponding segments.
让我们先对所有相应的片断作映射。
To map a segment,
we're going to click
为了对片断做映射，点击
on the dot next to
the segment name
片断名边上的点
and simply drag and
drop to the target.
然后简单的拖放到目标。
And then we can do this for
all the rest of the segments.
然后我们可以对剩下的片断重复该动作。
Notice down below,
now we have some text
注意到在底部有一些文本，
that corresponds with the
graphical editor above.
其对应着上面的图形编辑器。
This is a good practice to
get into to map each segment
对每个片断进行映射，
from the source to the target.
是一个非常好的实践活动。
Notice we don't have to
do the fields underneath,
注意到，在片断底下，没有看到字段，
because those are already done
automatically when you just
其原因是，当你映射片断时，
do the segment itself.
自动给你做了字段的映射。
Then, if we want to
change the target
然后，如果我们需要改变目标值
to be anything other
than the source,
到任何不同于源的值。
we can do so by using the
Add Action option at the top.
我们可以利用在顶部的 "Add" 动作。
We can add an "if" statement if
a decision has to made or set
我们可以添加一个 "if" 语句如果需要有个条件判定，
if we want to assign something
to a string constant.
或者一个 "set"， 如果我们需要设置一个字串的常量。
Let's take a look at
a few other options
让我们来看一下数据转换中的
that we have with
data transformations.
其他几个选项。
The first one is
using a function
第一个是使用一个函数，
to make all characters in
the patient's name uppercase.
可以改变病人的姓名字母为大写。
Let's first draw a line
mapping the patient's name
我们首先画一线将病人姓名
from the source to the target.
从源映射到目标。
We can then edit it to
apply function to it.
我们可以编辑它，将函数运用上。
We can use the magnifying
glass to edit this value.
我们可以利用放大镜来编辑这个值。
Here, the function that we
can choose is ToUpper().
这里，我们可以选用 ToUpper() 函数。
This will make the
whole name uppercase.
这个函数可使整个名字变成大写。
The second is using
a lookup table,
第二个，我们使用对照 (lookup) 表，
so male and female are
rendered as M and F.
因而，男性和女性可分别用 M 和 F表示。
Just like any other
function, lookup
如同其他的函数，lookup 可以
can be used to apply
a lookup table.
使用 lookup 表。
So let's first go to Sex,
and we can map that field
所以，我们首先到 Sex 然后从
from the source to the target.
源到目标映射这个字段。
Then on the right
hand side, we can edit
然后再右手边，我们可以编辑
this to apply our lookup table.
它，然后将 lookup 表运用其上。
From this wizard, we get the
option to choose our table.
从这个想到，有个选项可选择我们所要的表。
I've already set
up a lookup table
我已经设置好了一个 lookup 表，
that is going to do our
correct gender lookup.
这表可作我们的性别对照。
So I'm going to choose
that lookup table.
因此我们选在这张 lookup 表。
We can then choose what our
default option would be.
我们然后可以选则缺省选项。
Let's say, for us, the
default will be Unknown.
这里，对于我们，缺省为 Unknown.
So I'm simply going
to type in "U."
因而，我会简单得输入 "U".
The next option that I want to
talk about is concatenation.
对于下个选项，我想讲一下字串合并。
So for example, we can
take City and State
这个例子中，我们会拿城市和州
and put it into another field.
合并后放在另一个字段。
Notice here, we
do a simple assign
这里，我们注意到，我们只是做一个简单的赋值
even if the source and the
target are not the same names.
甚至源和目标字段不是同样的名字。
I can then concatenate another
field by using an underscore.
然后我可以用下划线合并另外一个字段。
So now our other
designation is going
所以，现在我们可指定另外一个值
to be the value of City
underscore State or Province.
为城市下划线州或者省。
So now my other
designation is going
因此，我们还制定一个值为，
to be my City comma
State or Province.
我的城市逗号州或者省。
Let's next talk about
our "if" option.
接下去，我们谈一下 "if" 选项。
I can use the "if" statement
to check if the SSN starts
我可以使用 "if" 语句来检查 SSN 是否
with three zeroes and then
assign our target to be invalid
以三个零开头，如果为真，
SSN if it is true.
那么目标 SSN 为无效。
Let's first check
our source field
让我们先看一下我们的源数据字段
and then add our action "if".
然后添加 "if" 动作。
So I'm going to click
SSN number patient
因此我会点击病人的 SSN 号码
and then choose Add Action "if".
然后选中 "Add Action" 的 "if"。
This will give me a
line to the center
在编辑框的中间会显示我们一行
with a diamond in the center.
并带有一个钻石符号。//////////////////////////////////////////////?????
By default, the
next assign that I
缺省情况下，我会在这
do is going to put this
in our if statement
语句中赋值，
if our condition is true.
如果条件为真。
Let's first set
up our condition.
让我们先来设置我们的条件。
We want to check to see if
our SSN starts with 000.
我们希望检查 SSN 是否以 000 开头。
StartsWith is a function.
这里使用 "StartsWith" 函数。
And I can supply 000 as an
argument to that function.
我们可以给这个函数填上 "000" 作为参数。
Notice that the
bottom of the screen,
注意到，在屏幕的底部，
we automatically
have an "if" with
自动给我们添上 "if" 和
this "StartsWith"
condition and an "else".
"StartsWith" 条件以及 "else" 的语句。
If I click on "else",
the following assignment
如果我点中 "else", 那么下面的赋值
will be evaluated if the
"if" condition is false.
语句会检查如果条件为假的情况。
But I would like to
assign, in this case,
但在这个例子中，我们想
if the "if" condition is true.
做的赋值为条件为真的情况。
So I will leave it on the "if".
所以我们会停留在 "if" 的子句上。///////////////////////////////////////?????
The next thing I want
to do is assign my SSN.
下件事情，我要做的是对 SSN 赋值。
So I'm going to click
on SSNNumberPatient
所以，我会点击 SSNNumberPatient
and then Add Action "set".
然后选中 "Add Add" 中的 "set"。
And I want to specify that
my value is "INVALID SSN".
我想指定其值为 "INVALID SSN"。
Again, notice on the bottom
my "if" is on line 22
同样，我们可以注意到在底部，22行上有 "if"
while my "set" is
line 23 indented,
同时我们的 "set" 在23行上缩进去的地方，
showing us that that "set" is
only going to occur if our "if"
这表明在 "set" 只有当 "if" 条件
condition is true.
为真时发生。
The last option that
I'm going to cover
最后我们要讲解的一个选项
is what to do with
repeating segments.
是如何处理重复的片段。
You'll notice that some
segments have some parentheses
你可能注意到有些片段在它们的名字后
at the end of the name, for
example NK1, next of kin.
带有括号，比如 NK1 (近亲)。
This means that we can
have multiple next of kin
这意味着，我们在 HL7 消息中
segments in my HL7 message.
可以有多个近亲的片断。
Clicking on this link, I
can tell my right hand side
点中这个连接，在我们的右手边
that my NK1 has the
parentheses that are empty.
NK1带有一个空括号。
If I wanted to
specify each NK1, I
如果我要指定每个 NK1,
can put a number in
those parentheses.
我可以在括号中添加具体数字。
For example, just to copy
over the first NK1 segment,
比如我只想复制第一个 NK1 片段，
I can type in one.
那么我就输入 1。
We can also use the
Add Action "for each"
我们也可以用 "Add Action" 中的 "for each",
if I want to do more
complicated things
如果我们要对重复片断
with my repeating segments.
做一些复杂处理。
Now that we have our
transformation set up,
现在，我们已设置好第一数据装换。
let's first compile
and then test it.
让我们编译并测试。
To test our
transformation, we can go
为了测试我们的数据转换，我们可进入
to the Tools tab and then Test.
工具 (Tools) 标签页，然后点击 "Test"。
Notice from this test
transform wizard,
注意，这里会有一个数据转换测试的向导。
I can copy and paste a message
that I have on my file system,
我可以复制粘贴消息在此，如果
possibly in a text document.
消息存放在一个文本文件中。
Then I can click Test.
然后我点击 Test.
Notice any segment
that has been changed
注意任何已经改变的片段，
is marked by a star
in the output message.
会在输出消息中带有星号。
For example, in
my input message,
比如在我们的输入消息中，
Massey and James
are both lowercase.
Massey 和 James 都是小写。
Notice in the output, Massey and
James are now both uppercase.
注意到，在输出重 Massey 和 James 都成大写了。
If we scroll over, we can also
see that although in our input
我们在滚动过去，看到虽然在输入消息中，
message we have our SSN
that starts with 000,
SSN 是以 000 开头的，
the output has changed to
have the value INVALID SSN.
但是输出重的值是 "INVALID SSN"。
We also applied a lookup table.
我们也应用了我们的 lookup 表。
Notice in the input
message we have
注意到，在我们输入的消息中有
"M", which is in the
output message also in "M".
"M", 在输出的消息也有。
If we want to
change this to test,
如果我们转换这，进行测试，
I can simply type in
"Male" in my input message
我简单地在输入消息中，输入 "Male"
and then click Test again.
然后再次点击测试。
Notice my output
message is still "M".
注意到，我的输出消息中还是 "M"。
It has correctly
transported "Male" to "M".
还是正确地将 "Male" 转换成了 "M"。
We can then apply this
HL7 Data Transformation
然后我们可以应用这个数据转换到
to our rules set
by editing a rule
我们的规则集中。我们需要编辑一个规则
and selecting it
for our transform
在数据发送到目标前，
before sending it to the target.
加上数据转换。
We hoped you learn
a little bit more
我们希望您能通过
about getting started with
HL7 Data Transformations.
这个 HL7 的数据转换课程
进一步学到一些知识。